A Guide to the Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society Records, 1968-2009
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society Records, 1968-2009
Thomas Balch Library
094
2 cubic feet.
The Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society (LRPS) was founded in 1967 to promote the recognition, restoration, and preservation of historical sites and buildings in Loudoun County. LRPS merged with the Preservation Society of Loudoun County in 2008. The collection contains minutes, the charter and by-laws for the society, lists of officers and board members, correspondence, legal and financial documents, as well as materials relating to August Court Days, restoration projects, and the 100th anniversary of celebration of the Leesburg courthouse.
Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
H. Vernon Davis, Leesburg, VA
Accruals
2013.0087
Historical Information
The Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society (hereafter referred to as LRPS) was founded in 1967 when the Town of Leesburg purchased two buildings with plans to raze them and create a parking lot. When research revealed one of the buildings was originally a log cabin constructed in the mid-1700s, Leesburg citizens took action and formed a committee called Committee for Leesburg. With the intent to restore and preserve historic buildings, they leased the log cabin as their headquarters for $1.00 per year. The Committee completed renovations and restorations to the two buildings in 1976, at which point one became Loudoun Museum, and the other the Committee’s headquarters. In 1974, the committee was incorporated as Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society.
To promote the recognition, restoration, and preservation of historical sites and buildings in Loudoun County, LRPS sponsored a historic plaque program in the city of Leesburg, and offered grants to organizations seeking to restore and preserve historic places. As of 2008, LRPS had given over $790,000 to 65 organizations for preservation work.
One of the ways LRPS drew funding for grants was through the annual August Court Days. Originally hosted by the Town of Leesburg in 1976 as a bicentennial celebration, August Court Days was a weekend of court trial reenactments from the late 1700s, a historically-based play, entertainment, and craft vendors. From 1977 to 2005, LRPS sponsored and organized the weekend, using the sales from tickets as a major source of grant monies donated. In 2007, the Town of Leesburg began hosting again and renamed it Court & Market Days, but discontinued holding it after 2008.
LRPS was run by an annually elected Board of Directors composed of the president, vice-president, secretary, and treasurer, and a Board of Trustees composed of no more than seventeen board members with three-year terms. The Board of Directors and the Board of Trustees organized August Court Days, approved grant monies, and worked in the wider Loudoun area to insure that historic sites were documented and preserved.
In 2008, the LRPS merged with the Preservation Society of Loudoun County, a group which focused on environmental preservation as well as historic building preservation. The merger was begun in 2008 and completed by 31 March 2009. The new organization is called Loudoun Preservation Society, and it covers all aspects of historical, cultural, and environmental preservation in Loudoun County.
Scope and Content
The collection contains minutes of regularly conducted meetings, the charter and by-laws for the society, lists of officers and board members, correspondence, treasurer’s reports, bank records, legal documents regarding filing for incorporation and permits to solicit contributions in Virginia, as well as copies of tax forms sent to the IRS. Additionally, there are plans for organizing August Court Days, and two video cassettes recording the 100th anniversary celebration of the Leesburg courthouse in 1994.
The records also contain documents on several restoration projects the LRPS sponsored such as the log cabin in Leesburg, the Black Horse Ordinary building in Leesburg, the Aldie Mill, the Ida Lee Parks Barn, the Courthouse Clock Tower, and grant requests from the 1980s through 2009.
Arrangement
Chronological
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society, (M 094), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection, (M 068), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Related Material
Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection, (M 068), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Contents List
  - 1
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1974-1977
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1991-1995
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 1996-1999
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 2000-2004
    - Board Meeting Minutes, 2005-2008
    - Corporate Charter and By-Laws
    - Officers and Board Members, 1989-2008
    - Correspondence, 1980-2005
    - Correspondence, 2006-2008
    - Treasurer's Reports/Financial Statements, 1993-2004
    - Bank Records, 1968-1971
    - Bank Records, 1972-1975
    - Summary of Grants and Restoration Project Expenses, 1980-2008
    - IRS Documents, 1993-2002
    - Business Membership Program, 2006
    - Informational Brochure
    - Virginia State Corporation Commission Registration, 2007
    - Virginia State Filings, 2007
    - Presentation to Leesburg Council, 1993
    - Hosts Preservation Alliance of Virginia, 1991
    - Loudoun History Award 2001
    - August Court Days, Brochures, 1976-2001
    - August Court Days, Fi9nancial Statements, 1998-2005
    - August Court Days, General Liability Policy, 2004-2005
  - 2
    - August Court Days, Information for Volunteers
    - August Court Days, Leesburg Town Ordinance, 1983
    - August Court Days, Planning, 1993-2002
    - August Court Days, Planning, 2005
    - August Court Days, Publicity, 1978-2006
    - August Court Days, Scrapbook (1/6), 1982-1989
    - August Court Days, Scrapbook (2/6), 1982-1989
    - August Court Days, Scrapbook (3/6), 1982-1989
    - August Court Days, Scrapbook (4/6), 1982-1989
    - August Court Days, Scrapbook (5/6), 1982-1989
    - August Court Days, Scrapbook (6/6), 1982-1989
    - August Court Days, Slides, Photo
    - Log Cabin Restoration, W. Loudoun St., Leesburg, 1975-1976
    - Ordinary Restoration, W. Market St., Leesburg, 1975-1976
    - Grants, Aldie Mill 1993
    - Grants, Ida Lee Park Barn 1993
    - Courthouse Clock Tower Project 1994
    - Courthouse Clock Tower Project, Individual Donations 1994
    - Courthouse Clock Tower Project, Ancillary Material, 1994
    - Miscellaneous Projects, 1975-1995
  - 3
    - Grants, 1980s
    - Grants, 1980s
    - Grants, 1990
    - Grants, 1992-
    - Grants, 1994-1995
    - Grants, 1996
    - Grants, 1998
    - Grants, 1999
    - Grants, 2000
    - Grants, 2000
    - Grants, 2001
    - Grants, 2001
    - Grants, 2002
    - Grants, 2002
    - Grants, 2003
    - Grants, 2004
    - Grants, 2004
    - Grants, 2004
    - Grants, 2005
    - Grants, 2005
    - Grants, 2005
    - Grants, 2006
  - 4
    - Grants, 2006
    - Grants, 2007
    - Grants, 2007
    - Grants, 2007
    - Grants, 2008
    - Grants, 2009
    - 100th Anniversary Courthouse Celebration (2 videotapes), 24 April 1994